Guide to the Archibald Bouton Negatives MC.404
New York University Archives
Archibald Bouton Negatives
circa 1900-1925
New York University Archives
Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941
MC.404
0.67 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and a half manuscript box
Archibald Lewis Bouton (1872-1941) was a Professor of Rhetoric (1905-1914), Professor of English (1914-1941), and the Dean of New York University's College of Arts and Science (1914-1935). The Archibald Bouton Negatives (circa 1900-1925) consists of photo negatives documenting Bouton's travels within the United Kingdom, France, and the United States.
Scope and Contents
The Archibald Bouton Negatives (circa 1900-1925) consists of photo negatives documenting Bouton's travels within the United Kingdom, France, and the United States. Locations photographed in this collection include, but are not limited to: London, York, Cambridge, Oxford, Warwick, Edinburgh, Versailles, Paris, Verdun, Reims, Pomona, Boston, Pittsburgh, and New York City.
Negatives related to the United States include negatives #1-7, #41-61 and #93-95. Negatives related to the United Kingdom include negatives #8-40 and negatives #62-82. Negatives related to France include negatives #83-92.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged in the order in which they were received. Negatives appear to be arranged roughly by geographic region.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were transferred from the New York University Archives Photograph Collection (PHOTO 00001) in May 2024. The accession number associated with this collection is 2024.045.
Biographical Note
Archibald Lewis Bouton was born on September 1, 1872 in Cortland, New York. He received his A.B. from Amherst in 1896 and his M.A. from Columbia in 1900. He first came to New York University in 1898 as an instructor of English. In 1901, he became an assistant professor and then a full professor in 1905. He served as the Professor of Rhetoric between 1905-1914. In 1914, Bouton became head of the English department and served in that position until 1941. Between 1914-1935, he was also the Dean of the College of Arts and Science. Bouton died on April 18, 1941 in Pasadena, California after having been Dean of University College for twenty-one years.
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the Dean, University College of Arts and Science (Archibald L. Bouton) (RG 18.0.2)
Negatives.; Travel photography.; England.; France.; United States.
- Inventory of Negatives, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Negatives #1-5, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  The titles of these negatives are: Around Cortland, House in Cortland and Around House, New York Apartment (112th Street), Around House - Cortland, and Florida Groups.
- Negatives #6-12, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  The titles of these negatives are: In Cortland, S.S. Arabia, Lichfield, Warwick, Kenilworth, Stratford, and Howardian.
- Negatives #13-20, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  The titles of these negatives are: Wales, English Lakes, Auchgoyle, Peter Laumont, Kyles of Bute from boat, and Pictures in Kerry.
- Negatives #21-31, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  The titles of these negatives are: Pictures in Kerry, Edinburgh and vicinity, Stirling and vicinity, Ayr and vicinity, Cannes, Near Cannes, London, Oxford, Elgin, and Cawdor Castle.
- Negatives #32-40, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  The titles of these negatives are: Culloden, Lamont Family Groups, Inverness to Oban, Oban to Tarbert, Clyde, Dunoon, Melrose, Dryburgh, and Whitfield (N.H.).
- Negatives #41-45, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  The titles of these negatives are: Cambridge (Mass.), Peterborough (1915), Peterborough (1921), Provincetown (1919), and Cloquet (1916).
- Negatives #46-49, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  The titles of these negatives are: Cloquet (1916), St. James (Minn.), Stamford (N.Y.), and 159th St (N.Y.C.)
- Negatives #50-53, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  The titles of these negatives are: 2206 Andrews Ave. (N.Y.C.) and House in Cortland.
- Negatives #54-58, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  The titles of these negatives are: AB Office in Cortland, Tripe to Pike Co. (P.A.), and 16 Dudley Place.
- Negatives #59-70, circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  The titles of these negatives are: 16 Dudley Place, Cemetery Stone - Cortland, Amherst 1917 (Mass.), F.G. Oakley, Interior Abbey, Glastonbury Abbey, Stonehenge and nearby, Salisbury Cathedral, Wells Cathedral and close, Ecclefechan, Flixtore [sic] and nearby, and Cortland (family).
- Negatives #71-82, circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  The titles of these negatives are: 2206 Andrews Ave., 16 Dudley Place, Loch Katrina, Ardrishaig, Ardlamont, Berwick-upon-Tweed, Cambridge, London, York, Ely, Boston, and Oxford.
- Negatives #83-92, circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  The titles of these negatives are: Paris, Châlons-sur-Marne, Verdun and region, Reims and region, Chartres, Versailles, Durban, Luceolu [sic], Voyage to Quebec, and Dausville.
- Negatives #93-95, circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  The titles of these negatives are: Woodstock, Transcontinental, and Pomona.